[Music]
yesterday we began
to explain some building blocks balls
spheres and we said that we can combine
these building blocks to make
interesting useful manifolds how do we
combine them those are the operations
that we shall discuss and effectively
there are three operations operation
number one
is that of
product that's in many ways the
simplest the primary example it's
example two by the way because we
already had um and remark one earlier so
we can refer to these things
is the example of an M Cube so M
dimensional Cube what this
is is simply this I you remember what I
is it's the unit interval from 0 to one
the close unit interval and it is simply
equal to what many people call the
cartisian product or direct product with
M components of I and this if you
remember the meaning of this symbol it's
homeomorphic to or topologically the
same as you can see that it
is homeomorphic to the m dimension of
all mble here are some examples the
onedimensional
cube is
simply the unit interal two dimensional
cube is what we more commonly called the
square 0
one unit Square
each side has length one and three
dimensional cube is what in the common
da language we would call a cube Rubik
Cube and that kind of thing and please
note that this cube is a full cube there
is inside as well as outside because I'm
taking the whole unit so that's the
standard cube in R3 but we can consider
higher dimension of cubes and these will
be useful from time to time okay now
the Box this is kind of a box if you
like and the Box surface so the boundary
of this thing without the
inside is there's a notation for this
the boundary of
this Cube if you want to be completely
careful you can put parentheses around
there but that's not and this is of
course homeomorphic
2 a sphere but sphere of what
dimension M minus one dimension drops by
one as we mentioned before that's
correct good so that's what it is okay
next another equally good example ah I
forgot to bring an example of this but
anyway it's an M dimensional Taurus and
we often call it m tus you have been
noticing that instead of saying M
dimensional something we often say m
something that's because mathematicians
are
lazy they sometimes talk too much but
not when it's it's appropriate so M
torus
is denoted by T to M so that's the
dimension and that is by definition
equal to we took the product of unit
intervals this time we are going to take
the product of unit circles so again M
factors now what does this animal look
like here is what it looks like when m
is one T1 is a single Circle so that's
easy
to picture that's a
circle what is T2 T2 has two
meanings you can imagine a circle times
a circle or here is one way to think
about it take a
circle and then move this circle all the
way around in a circular
way and when you do this you have the
product of circle times a circle as
represented inside a threedimensional
space so this
T2 is what is often drawn like this and
it's a
Taurus now do you have a good mental
picture of what a Taurus is can you see
what the Taurus is this picture is very
popular around the world but it's not
the most
obvious picture so let me make it really
clear again imagine a circle just a
circle not the inside not the disc but
the circle and move this circle like
this yeah and move all the way around
like a surface of Revolution and then
close you get this kind of donut shape
if you're used to American donuts I I
recognize that in some other countries
Donuts don't look like this and the
surface of this donut surface of this
donut is the Taurus and that's a two-
dimensional
Taurus all right another meaning of T2
is tadash to I mean you know it's a when
you write my
name well you write it as T do T that
looks like T * T so I often sign T squ
but but it's it's not applicable to the
rest of mathematics okay so that's t t^
s okay and you should realize that this
Taurus can come in many different shapes
for example as far as the topology is
concerned this
Taurus can be represented in a very
strange position in space for example
like that imagine a cube which is
entangling with itself but that's okay
as long as it's an Hollow tube and its
topology surface has that of Taurus that
is also a Taurus another classic
example is this you drank probably in
the last 24 hours from a
cup and a standard mug looks like this
do you know the word
mug mu ug mug means this kind of chunky
straight cup from which you drink you
can call it a cup but a more common
English word is mug anyway so if you
look at the surface of this it is in
fact homeomorphic to a Taurus it's
really strange but true and it's a
standard popular magazine example of
what a Taurus is
okay so cubes and Tor the plural of a
Taurus is a
toai t o r i
now let
let mention one interesting fact about
the product since we're talking about
products of manifolds let's say that we
have two manifolds M and N whatever they
are and we want to find out the
dimension of M * n the product in terms
of the dimensions of M and and of n how
does that work well that's very
easy it's the sum of the
dimensions so in a way dimension
behaves like logarithm that's
interesting
okay that's quite straightforward you
see if you have a two dimensional space
and three dimensional space and you take
the product the total space is going to
be five dimensional that's
e next on the topic of
products we have some very useful um
symbols last time do you remember
boundary and the homomorphic
homomorphism we have already used but we
have not yet looked at the boundary
operation let's ask how
does the boundary
operator operate on or act on
products
namely what is the boundary of the
product of two
manifolds if you have some manifold with
boundary another manifold with the
boundary you can think about surface or
curve or whatever boundary sorry
manifold time manifold and you take the
boundary can you express it in terms of
the boundaries of the individual
factors now lots of people think that it
is
the product of the boundaries but that's
not true and we shall see in a moment
that it's not true instead it's
something much more interesting it is
equal to the boundary of the first
Factor together with the whole of the
second manifold
sorry times the whole of the second
manifold and together with Union whole
of the first manifold times the boundary
of the
second who recognizes this kind of
formula who has seen something like this
before we all
have
where
huh
where of distributive law of
differentiation that's right so
note that the boundary operator
yeah acts according to the lightness
role that's what it's called of
of do you know Mr light
it for differentiating a product in this
case of course differentiating a product
of functions
differen she a yeah I was explaining
correct
products but that analogy carries over
to the manifolds and this analogy is not
accidental there's a deep reason for
this
analogy when you Lear mathematics Aro Mo
there's a very
beautiful set of result Theory Theory
called Duram
[Applause]
kology and in that theory you see the
analogy there's an exact sort of
Correspondence between drums the okay so
let's prove
this this
result how
the um product the the boundary operator
excuse me acts on the product and this
we shall call theorem number
four okay so the proof of theorem number
four you've guessed it it's by
pictures so let's take the product of
two manifolds I'm going to say
that this is say my picture for M it
looks like just an interal but that's
okay we are drawing a nice conceptual
picture and that's my picture for
n okay and what does the product of
these two things look like well if these
are both literally intervals the product
looks of course like a
rectangle whose sides are respectively M
and N okay so that's the M cross
n now we we like to take the boundary of
this this
thing what is that well boundary of this
Bo box with the inside is very easy it's
simply equal
to
this just that and this is
again where M and N are okay so that's
what it is but what is this we can write
this in the following
fashion this is equal
to first look at this
m but look at the boundary of
M so that's
the boundary of M if this is M that's
the boundary M and the whole of
N and if you take the direct product
of these two points and this what you
get is just this part which is the
product of this point and this n and
this part which is the product of that
point and this nend okay
union now I'm going to take the boundary
of this side which is n so here are the
boundary points in this case but in
general any dimension of n so that's the
boundary of N and this time all of M
will be taken so this is all of M and
what is the product of these two picture
it is equal to
well this which is the product of M and
this point and this which is the product
of this m and this point and you see
that if you take the union of this and
this you get presso the whole box and
that is exactly what's going on and this
concludes our
proof okay
[Applause]
okay you know the abbreviation
QED yeah what does it stand
for Quad era
[Music]
demonstrandum this is what was to be
demonstrated is the class Co
interpretation but there's a new modern
version you can call it
quite easily done
that's an example of a
QED
okay now let's
revisit examples two and
three that
is cubes and
Tor
okay we direct apply this theorem and
test
if um this the works on those examples
this boundary operator so what's the
boundary of the Box well it is simply
equal to according to this liance
law the M factors in this product so I
take the boundary of the first factor
and then I take the union
with boundary of the second
Factor okay let me not put parenthesis
here but I'm I'm going to put the
parenthesis like this parenthesis like
this and then Union and I keep taking
the union and finally the last factor is
I get the
product and then product of I can you
see what I'm writing at this end of the
black boat I'm sorry I'm about to run
out of space but 50 into one line so
that's what it is okay so in picture
it's probably easier to see let's take
this threedimensional example
that's a cube and remember that this
Cube has an inside yeah it's a full cube
what is the boundary of this well we
know what the boundary of this is It's
the surface of the Cube It's the surface
of the box but let's write down the
answer according to our formula and see
if it makes sense what does this mean it
means that if this is the x y z
directions first I take the boundary of
the interval in the X Direction in other
words I'm taking in the X Direction only
this point and this point so the two
surfaces that we are seeing are only
those
surfaces over the cube so this
surface and this surface I hope you can
see the
picture Okay so that's the first term
and the second term is I'm going to take
the boundary of the unit interval in the
y direction and that gives me two
surfaces that facing those
ways same Cube but I'm picking out pairs
of surfaces each time faces each time
excuse me and
finally third term is the boundary of
the Zed axis unit interval and those
will correspond
to those two surfaces top and
bottom
okay and if you put all of these
surfaces together or faces together you
see that you are reconstructing the
entire surface of the box so that shows
the theorem is
true
okay next
example what about the boundary of a
Taurus that's easily calculated even
more easily than the previous example
because look the definition of torus is
that it's a product of circles if I
apply the lights rule which you very
much very well identified you take the
boundary of this boundary of this and
then you add them all up but what is the
boundary of a
circle H what's the boundary of a
circle
huh boundary of a circle is a
circumference then my name is not Tashi
TOA so what's the boundary of a circle
does the circle have a
boundary
huh no it's not the same it doesn't have
a boundary it has no boundary because
you don't you never come to a stop when
you're walking on a circle you are
probably confusing a circle with
something else called a disc weren't you
yes you are well we said yesterday
didn't we that everyone is confused
about discs and circles I don't mean the
dis as in the whole thing included in
the middle the bound boundary of the dis
is the circle but boundary of the circle
which is the curve there's nothing it's
the empty
set yeah boundary means that you keep
walking and then you have to come to
stop because you can't go any further
well on the circle you can keep walking
walking you never have to stop on the
surface of a
dis as long as you are walking over here
you don't have to stop but when you come
here whoop you have to stop otherwise
you fall out of the universe that's the
boundary okay so boundary of a circle is
the empty set therefore all those terms
are empty with the result that the
boundary of Taurus is empty in other
words the Taurus does not have a
boundary it is a closed surface as we
call it
of does that make sense yes it does
because if you think about the Taurus
this picture of a donut does he have a
boundary no if you are an ant an insect
walking on this surface you can keep
walking walking and there will never be
a time when you come to a boundary and
have to stop there is no boundary on
this thing again please do not make the
mistake of thinking that this Taurus
represents a real donut with the inside
to
eat I realize that temptation is great
but this is disappointingly a hollow
donut there's nothing inside to eat it
is only the surface and so there's no
boundary if you had what is called a
solid Taurus real donut with the inside
then this that object would have a
boundary the boundary is this Taurus
surface itself
okay good we have now covered quite a
lot of ground let's keep going and I'd
like to insert an
interesting
digression in order to exert ourselves
in visualization can you see this small
writing you have all perfect vision so
you can I wouldn't be able
to consider the following interesting
problem I start
with a
square and inside the square I'm going
to put
four discs of equal size as large as I
can manage in the four corners of this
square is that okay
yeah after I do
this there's some space in the middle so
I'm going to put the largest this that I
I can I can in the middle
space let's say that I started with a
square of side one so unit Square
I2 in I2 in
was um Place pack
four eal
discs in the
corners and place as large as a disc as
you
can and
fit a disk and this dis is this uh this
in the
middle in the middle
okay everyone comfortable with this
construction I
hope question what is the
diameter of this middle
dis what is it if the side of one of the
square is one well you can solve this
problem in a multiple ways but I think
this is one of the cleanest
let's copy this picture over and over
again by which I mean you know we have
been we are doing this in
one corner of the plane but let's copy
it all over the
place cut and paste if you like as you
would be able to do on the
computer and you can just copy this
picture all over the place like this
yeah now in this copy there are lots and
lots of copies of the central dis
there's it's here it's here it's here
yeah do you see this periodic
picture and then it keeps
going this shows how to comput it we
know the length of this diagonal which
is square root of two and if you think
about this copy not only is there this
orange disc here but there is part of
the orange disc over here and part of
the orange disc over
here okay so what is the diameter of
this it is simply equal to squ root of
two which is the diagonal of this large
thing
minus you see the part of the disc you
seeing here
has only one quarter of it protruding
inside similarly here one quarter so if
you put this length and this length you
get the diameter of the dis
okay and there's another diameter of dis
there so there are two diameters of the
dis we have to divide by two why did I
subtract one because that's the amount
that's occupied by those two big discs
the diameter of this disc is half why is
it half because if I turn it like this
look it's 1 12 if I turn it like this
it's 1 12 okay so what we don't want is
one 12+ 1 12 that's one and then the
remaining thing is represented by two
diss worth so that's one so what is this
do you know the square root of
two 1
4 4 2
1 3 5 6
[Music]
2 - one/ 2 and that's approximately
equal to
0.2 and that's certainly less than One
what does it mean to be less than one
that simply means that this disc in the
middle is smaller than this Square well
of course because we put it inside the
square okay so that's what it is now
let's do the same in higher dimensional
space do the same in not I2 but I m in
the M dimensional space here is a
picture in 3D 3D means 3 Dimensions if
you have a cube think about three
dimensional Cube then you can put how
many big balls in the corners how many
corners are
there come on eight eight Corners so we
put eight balls here here here here here
and here and you cannot quite see the
balls in the back okay and
inside you you
put this middle ball
hiding
okay did you notice that I said dis in
2D and ball in 3D it's in order to get
used to the language you can call it
ball in any Dimension now in this case
what is the
diameter of the middle ball what do you
think
do you have imagination to do the same
copying but in three
dimensions let's say you have a box Cube
here have another Cube here whose corner
is touching this corner another Cube
here another Cube here another Cube here
going up diagonally you
see that picture will allow us to
compute find out the diameter of the
middle B because what you have to do
well it's exactly the same AR argument
that we invented over there you look at
the diagonal of this cube in 3D what's
the length of the diagonal of a unit
cube do you know Pythagoras in 2D
diagonal of a unit cube of length one
and one is square root of two in 3D what
is
it
almost speak up you have such a be
beautiful voice it's a Pity to waste
it square root of three he says speak up
even more it's a you a great scientist
and you should pronounce yourself so
Square three and in dimension n m excuse
me what's going to square m is that okay
because the sum so the square of the
diagonal is the sum of the squares of
the size Pythagoras so this is equal to
instead of square of two we have square
Ro of M minus one it's exactly the same
magment over
two okay in MD M
Dimensions what is curious is that this
number increases with
M and when m
is 10 or above it is greater than
one indeed when m is 9 s Ro of 9 is 3 3
- 1 2 2 ID two is 1 so beyond nine from
10 upward
this is greater
than one what does that
mean this
[Music]
means that the
middle
ball is sticking outside the cube
so the cartoon picture would be like
this you have a cube and you put balls
in the corner and in the space that
looks really tiny inside I started
putting fitting the middle middle
bow and so you think that this middle
ball is inside a cube but it isn't it's
actually sticking out on the side like
this in dimension 10 and above
so in higher dimensional spaces lots of
interesting things can
happen
Okay no we are using the M dimensional
bols in dimension
M you remember the building blocks that
I explained balls exist in all
Dimensions it just so happens in a very
particular case of two Dimensions it's
called a
dis in 3D you have seen it since
childhood but in any Dimension it exist
by the way in dimension one the one
dimensional ball is the interval between
minus one and one so don't be mised by
the words but realize that those balls
in any Dimension they most behave the
same way and they all are usedful in all
Dimensions so you know many of us have
this dimensional complex should I say
you know we feel very comfortable in 3D
a little comfortable in 2D but we feel
very very lonely and shivering and so
forth in dimension four and above that's
crazy you should feel comfortable in any
dimensions for example you should all
feel comfortable in dimension
145 okay